Jamie Smith

Executive Summary | Data Scientist Manager

Data scientist & product development leader with a proven track record of delivering valuable insights to clients and organizational leaders. I strive to drive client success through meaningful storytelling, well researched product development, and bringing data to life

Education

UC Berkeley, Berkeley, CA (4.0 GPA)

Expected Graduation Date May 2022

- Master of Information & Data Science
- Relevant Coursework: Machine Learning, Statistics, Field Experiments, Machine Learning, Regression, & Data Visualization

Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, VA

Graduated May 2010

- Bachelor of Science: Industrial and Systems Engineering, Minor: Business
- Recipient of full four year merit scholarship based on scholastic achievements

Work Experience

Google, Mountain View, CA

January 2015 - Present

Reporting & Insights, People Analytics Manager

March 2020 - Present

Manage a team of Data Scientists supporting Google's strategic people initiatives with a focus on Organizational Health and Diversity leveraging Machine Learning, Field Experiments and Regression techniques to derive insights (Top 3% last 2 years of performance cycles)

- Product lead responsible for the development of Org Health tools at scale leveraging People Analytics best practices and research to enable deployment of Org Health across People Operations with an estimated savings of 10K hours per year
- Led Future of Work research to discover best practices for working from home, focusing on Google's Sales Organization, while also building internal product solutions based off of these research findings

Reporting & Insights, People Analyst Lead

August 2018 - March 2020

Collected, studied, and interpreted large data sets to provide analytical support across the People domain for Google's sales (GBO) function. Advise and present to Google's Chief Business Officer, Philipps Schindler, monthly, on various people topics to enable the workforce to better achieve strategic goals

- Led research to unlock various people initiatives across domains such as attrition, diversity & inclusion, and talent development
- Created a number of forecasting tools to predict workforce trends to identify areas for additional investment

Reporting & Insights, Senior People Analyst

March 2017 - August 2018

- Developed advanced forecasting tools to determine future level mix, representation, and global footprint enabling leaders to create interventions across the organization saving the company an estimated \$8M
- Created first of its kind diversity dashboard providing all directors and VPs (~200 leaders) in Google's Sales Organization the ability to track progress against aspirational goals related to diversity initiatives

Google Fiber, Technical Program Manager

January 2015 - February 2017

Managed a team of 5 Technical PgMs responsible for the development of systems, tools and reports critical for tracking capital expenditures for the Google Fiber build efforts, comprising of a \$130M+ portfolio

- Led a team of 5 in successfully launching tableau dashboards for capex reports for the Google Fiber build activities comprising of a \$130M+ portfolio
- Managed Google Fiber vendor relationships for system deployments, financial transactions, and training efforts

Accenture Management Consulting, Washington, D.C.

August 2010- December 2014

IT Strategy Consultant

Led a number of federal and commercial engagements with a focus on data-driven strategic planning to bring value to clients through accelerated processes and increased IT capabilities. Example projects include:

- Developed and implemented the strategy for identifying resource needs across a quickly growing, industry leading geospatial imagery organization resulting from the acquisition of its largest competitor
- Led a quantitative IT Strategy engagement to determine the best approach for combining business needs with go-to-market IT specific enhancements which led to a three year reduction in the company's timeline for the IT launch

Extracurricular Activities

Black Google Network, San Francisco, CA Member

January 2015 - Present

Active participant of Google's internal affinity group focused on building an inclusive workplace for communities of color

Commonwealth of Scholars, Blacksburg, VA, Co-Founder

October 2007 - May 2010

Founded an honors organization for the enhancement and development of minorities on the Virginia Tech campus. Scholarships were awarded to the 40+ members of the organization and as cofounder was recognized by the Virginia State governor

<u>Skills:</u> **Advanced** in Spreadsheets, SQL, Product Development. **Proficient** in Field Experiments, Machine Learning, R, Python, Tableau <u>Interests:</u> Leadership, Mentorship, Education, Diversity & Inclusion, Technology, Startups, Volunteering with youth, Basketball, Football